When my father and I started a company
عندما بدأنا انا و والدي شركة
to 3D print human tissues and organs,
للطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد للأعضاء و الأنسجة البشرية
some people initially thought we were a little crazy.
إعتقد بعض الناس في البداية أننا قد جننا قليلاً
But since then, much progress has been made,
ولكن منذ ذلك الحين، أحرز الكثير من التقدم،
both in our lab and other labs around the world.
سواء في المختبر لدينا وفي مختبرات أخرى حول العالم.
And given this, we started getting questions like,
ونظرا لهذا، بدأنا نحصل على أسئلة مثل
"If you can grow human body parts,
إن كان بإمكانك أن تنمي أجزاء الجسم البشري
can you also grow animal products like meat and leather?"
هل يمكنك أيضا زراعة المنتجات الحيوانية مثل اللحوم والجلود؟
When someone first suggested this to me,
عندما إفترح شخص هذا لي
quite frankly I thought they were a little crazy,
إعتقدت في بادئ الامر انه مجنون قليلاً
but what I soon came to realize
ولكن سرعان ما أدركت
was that this is not so crazy after all.
ان هذه الفكرة لم تكن مجنونة
What's crazy is what we do today.
بل الجنون ما نقوم به اليوم.
I'm convinced that in 30 years,
أنا مقتنع تماماً أنه بعد 30 عاماً
when we look back on today
عندما نتذكر يومنا هذا
and on how we raise and slaughter billions of animals
و كيف كنا نربي و نذبح بلايين الحيوانات
to make our hamburgers and our handbags,
لصنع الحقائب و الهامبرجر
we'll see this as being wasteful
سوف نرى أن هذا إسراف
and indeed crazy.
و بالفعل جنون.
Did you know that today we maintain
هل تعلم أننا اليوم نمتلك
a global herd of 60 billion animals
قطيع عالمي مكوّن من 60 بليون حيوان
to provide our meat, dairy, eggs and leather goods?
لتوفير منتجات اللحوم، ومنتجات الألبان والبيض والجلود؟
And over the next few decades,
وعلى مدى العقود القليلة القادمة،
as the world's population expands to 10 billion,
سيتسع سكان العالم إلى 10 بلايين
this will need to nearly double
و بالتالي سنحتاج إلى ما يقارب الضعف
to 100 billion animals.
أي 100 بليون حيوان.
But maintaining this herd
ولكن الحفاظ على هذا القطيع
takes a major toll on our planet.
يأخذ ثمناً كبيراً من كوكبنا.
Animals are not just raw materials.
الحيوانات ليست فقط مواد خام
They're living beings,
بل كائنات حية
and already our livestock
والثروة الحيوانية لدينا الآن
is one of the largest users of land,
هي واحدة من أكبر مستخدمي الأراضي
fresh water,
المياه العذبة
and one of the biggest producers of greenhouse gases
وواحدة من أكبر منتجي الغازات التي تؤدي للإحتباس الحراري
which drive climate change.
و التي تؤدي إلى التغييرات المناخية
On top of this,
وعلاوة على ذلك
when you get so many animals so close together,
عندما نقوم بحصر عدد كبير من الحيوانات في مساحة ضيقة
it creates a breeding ground for disease
فإن ذلك يخلق أرضاً خصبة للأمراض
and opportunities for harm and abuse.
و فرص الأذى و الإعتداء.
Clearly, we cannot continue on this path
ومن الواضح، انه لا يمكننا مواصلة هذا الطريق
which puts the environment, public health,
الذي يعرض البيئة و الصحة العامة
and food security at risk.
والأمن الغذائي إلى الخطر.
There is another way, because essentially,
هناك طريقة أخرى لأنه في الأساس
animal products are just collections of tissues,
هذه المنتجات الحيوانية مجرد مجموعات من الأنسجة
and right now we breed and raise
والآن نحن نربي و نعتني
highly complex animals
بحيوانات بالغة التعقيد
only to create products
فقط لخلق منتجات
that are made of relatively simple tissues.
تصنع من أنسجة بسيطة نسبياً.
What if, instead of starting with a complex
ماذا لو، بدلاً من البدء
and sentient animal,
بحيوان ذا حس عال
we started with what the tissues are made of,
بدأنا بما تصنع الأنسجة
the basic unit of life,
الوحدة الأساسية للحياة
the cell?
الخلية ؟
This is biofabrication, where cells themselves
هذه الفبركة الحيوية حيث يتم إستخدام نفس هذه الخلايا
can be used to grow biological products
لزراعة المنتجات البيولوجية
like tissues and organs.
مثل الأنسجة والأعضاء.
Already in medicine,
بالفعل في الطب
biofabrication techniques have been used
تم استخدام تقنيات الفبركة الحيوية
to grow sophisticated body parts,
لزراعة اجزاء الجسم المعقدة
like ears, windpipes, skin, blood vessels and bone,
مثل الاذن و القصبة الهوائية والجلد والأوعية الدموية والعظام
that have been successfully implanted into patients.
والتي تم زراعتها بنجاح داخل المرضى.
And beyond medicine, biofabrication can be
و الفبركة الحيوية يمكن ان تصبح
a humane, sustainable and scalable new industry.
صناعة جديدة إنسانية ومستدامة وقابلة للتطوير.
And we should begin by reimagining leather.
وينبغي أن نبدأ من الجلود
I emphasize leather because it is so widely used.
وقمت بالتركيز على الجلد لأنه يتم استخدامه على نطاق واسع
It is beautiful, and it has long been a part of our history.
فهو جميل ،و طالما كان جزءاً من تاريخنا.
Growing leather is also technically simpler
زراعة الجلد أيضا أبسط من الناحية التقنية
than growing other animal products like meat.
من زراعة المنتجات الحيوانية مثل اللحوم.
It mainly uses one cell type,
فهي في الأساس تستخدم نوعاً واحداً من الخلايا
and it is largely two-dimensional.
و إلى حد كبير هي عملية ثنائية الأبعاد.
It is also less polarizing for consumers and regulators.
وهي أيضا أقل إستقطاباً للمستهلكين والهيئات التنظيمية.
Until biofabrication is better understood,
حتى يتم فهم الفبركة الحيوية بصورة أفضل
it is clear that, initially at least,
فمن الواضح أنه في البداية على الأقل
more people would be willing to wear novel materials
سيكون الناس على استعداد أكبر لإرتداء هذه المواد الجديدة
than would be willing to eat novel foods,
من إستعدادهم على تناولها
no matter how delicious.
مهما كانت لذيذة.
In this sense, leather is a gateway material,
و على هذا الأساس فإن الجلد سيكون البوابة
a beginning for the mainstream biofabrication industry.
لبداية إنتشار صناعة الفبركة الحيوية.
If we can succeed here,
إن كان بإمكاننا النجاح هنا
it brings our other consumer bioproducts like meat
فإن المنتجات الحيوية الإستهلاكية الإسهلاكية الأخرى مثل اللحم
closer on the horizon.
سيزيد الإقبال عليها.
Now how do we do it?
الآن كيف نفعل ذلك؟
To grow leather, we begin by taking cells
لنزرع الجلد، نبدأ بأخذ خلايا من حيوان
from an animal, through a simple biopsy.
عن طريق أخد خزعة (عينة) بسيطة.
The animal could be a cow,
يمكن أن يكون هذا الحيوان بقرة،
lamb, or even something more exotic.
خروف، أو حتى شيء أكثر غرابة.
This process does no harm,
هذه العملية غير مؤذية
and Daisy the cow can live a happy life.
و البقرة (دايسي) يمكن أن تعيش حياة سعيدة.
We then isolate the skin cells
ثم نقوم بعزل خلايا الجلد
and multiply them in a cell culture medium.
و نقوم بمكاثرتها في وسط مستنبت للخلايا.
This takes millions of cells
هذا يأخذ ملايين خلايا
and expands them into billions.
و يكاثرهم إلى بلايين الخلايا.
And we then coax these cells to produce collagen,
و بعد ذلك نحرّض هذه الخلايا لتنتج لكولاجين
as they would naturally.
كما تفعل في طبيعة الحال.
This collagen is the stuff between cells.
الكولاجين هي المادة التي تكون بين هذه الخلايا.
It's natural connective tissue.
هو نسيج طبيعي متصل.
It's the extracellular matrix,
و هو ما يصاحب هذه المصفوفة الخليوية
but in leather, it's the main building block.
ولكن في الجلود، هو كتلة المبنى الرئيسي.
And what we next do is we take the cells and their collagen
بعدها نقوم بأخذ الخلايا والكولاجين الخاص بهم
and we spread them out to form sheets,
وننشرهم ليشكلوا شكل ورقي
and then we layer these thin sheets on top of one another,
و من ثم نقوم بوضع هذه الأوراق الرقيقة فوق بعضها البعض على شكل طبقات
like phyllo pastry, to form thicker sheets,
مثل المعجنات (الباسطة)، لتشكل أوراق أكثر سمكاً
which we then let mature.
و التي نتركها فيما بعد لتنضج
And finally, we take this multilayered skin
وأخيراً، نأخذ هذا الجلد متعدد الطبقات
and through a shorter and much less chemical tanning process,
وعن طريق عمليات كيميائية و دباغة قليلة
we create leather.
نتحصل على الجلود.
And so I'm very excited to show you,
وأنا متحمس جداً لأريكم
for the first time,
للمرة الأولى
the first batch of our cultured leather,
أول دفعة من الجلود المزروعة لدينا
fresh from the lab.
طازجة من المختبر.
This is real, genuine leather,
هذا جلد حقيقي و أصلي
without the animal sacrifice.
دون التضحية بالحيوان.
It can have all the characteristics of leather
يمكن أن يحتوي على كافة الخصائص للجلود
because it is made of the same cells,
لأنه مصنوع من نفس الخلايا،
and better yet,
والأفضل من ذلك،
there is no hair to remove,
ليس هنالك شعر لإزالته
no scars or insect's bites,
لا ندوب أو لدغات حشرات
and no waste.
و بدون إهدار.
This leather can be grown in the shape of a wallet,
يمكن زراعة هذه الجلود على شكل محفظة ،
a handbag or a car seat.
حقيبة يد أو على شكل مقعد سيارة.
It is not limited to the irregular shape of a cow
ليس محدوداً على شكل مثل البقرة
or an alligator.
أو التمساح.
And because we make this material,
و لأننا نتدخل في عملية صناعة هذا الجلد
we grow this leather from the ground up,
من البداية إلى النهاية
we can control its properties in very interesting ways.
يمكن أن نتحكم بخصائصه بطرق مثيرة جداً للاهتمام.
This piece of leather
هذه القطعة من الجلد
is a mere seven tissue layers thick,
هي نسيج سمكه مكوّن من سبع طبقات تقريباً
and as you can see, it is nearly transparent.
وكما ترون، شفاف تقريباً
And this leather is 21 layers thick and quite opaque.
وهذا الجلد مكوّن من 21 طبقات و بالتالي غامق تماماً.
You don't have that kind of fine control
لم يكن لدينا هذا النوع من التحكم
with conventional leather.
مع الجلود التقليدية.
And we can tune this leather for other desirable qualities,
و بإمكاننا توليف هذه الجلود للحصول على الجودة والصفات المرغوب فيها
like softness, breathability,
المثل الليونة و قابلية التنفس
durability, elasticity and even things like pattern.
المتانة و المرونة وحتى صفات مثل النمط.
We can mimic nature,
يمكننا محاكاة الطبيعة
but in some ways also improve upon it.
بل و بإمكاننا في بعض الاحيان تحسينها.
This type of leather can do what today's leather does,
هذا النوع من الجلود يمكنه القيام بنفس ما تقوم به جلود اليوم
but with imagination, probably much more.
ولكن مع الخيال ربما يقوم بأكثر من ذلك بكثير.
What could the future of animal products look like?
كيف سيكون شكل المنتجات الحيوانية في المستقبل ؟
It need not look like this,
يجب تكون مثل هذا
which is actually the state of the art today.
وهو في الواقع حالة من الفن هذه الأيام.
Rather, it could be much more like this.
بل يمكنه ان يكون أكثر مثل هذا.
Already, we have been manufacturing with cell cultures
الآن بالفعل قمنا بصناعة مستعمرات الخلية
for thousands of years, beginning with products
لآلاف السنين ، بدءاً بالمنتجات
like wine, beer and yogurt.
مثل النبيذ والبيرة والزبادي.
And speaking of food, our cultured food has evolved,
و بالحديث عن الغذاء، فإن ثقافة الغذاء لدينا تطوّرت
and today we prepare cultured food
واليوم نحن نعد الغذاء
in beautiful, sterile facilities like this.
في مرافق جميلة و معقّمة مثل هذه.
A brewery is essentially a bioreactor.
مصنع البيرة هو في الأساس مفاعل حيوي.
It is where cell culture takes place.
حيث يتم فيه إستخدام مبادئ مستعمرات الخلايا.
Imagine that in this facility,
تخيل لو أنه في هذه المرفق
instead of brewing beer,
بدلاً من تحضير البيرة
we were brewing leather
نقوم بتحضير الجلود
or meat.
أو اللحوم.
Imagine touring this facility,
تخيل القيام بجولة في هذه المرافق
learning about how the leather or meat is cultured,
حيث نتعلم كيفية إستزراع هذه الجلود أو اللحوم،
seeing the process from beginning to end,
رؤية العملية من البداية إلى النهاية،
and even trying some.
وحتى تجربة البعض منها.
It's clean, open and educational,
أنها نظيفة ومفتوحة و تعليمية
and this is in contrast to the hidden,
و هذا على نقيض المصانع
guarded and remote factories
المخفية و البعيدة و الخاضعة للحراسة المشددة
where leather and meat is produced today.
حيث يتم إنتاج الجلود واللحوم اليوم.
Perhaps biofabrication
ولعل الفبركة الحيوية
is a natural evolution of manufacturing for mankind.
هي التطور الطبيعي للصناعات التحويلية للجنس البشري.
It's environmentally responsible,
و هي مسئولة بيئياً،
efficient and humane.
ذات كفاءة عالية وإنسانية.
It allows us to be creative.
أنها تسمح لنا بأن نكون مبدعين.
We can design new materials, new products,
يمكننا تصميم مواد جديدة، منتجات جديدة،
and new facilities.
ومرافق جديدة.
We need to move past just killing animals
نحتاج أن نتوقف عن مبدأ قتل الحيوانات
as a resource
كأحد الموارد
to something more civilized and evolved.
إلى شيء أكثر تحضر و تطور.
Perhaps we are ready for something
ربما نحن على إستعداد لشيء
literally and figuratively more cultured.
بالمعنى الحرفي و المجازي أكثر ثقافة.
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)